Guide to the Cuban Revolution Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Andrew St. George Photographs, Films, and Papers, 1957-1960; Series I
  - Photographs
    - Contact Book VI
      - Book VI Print 73: Fidel Castro giving televised speech denouncing Huber Matos; American Society of Travel Agents convention in Havana, 1959 October (Box 4, Folder 442)
        Top rows of images show Fidel Castro giving a televised address to the nation on October 19, 1959, in which he denounced Commander Huber Matos of treason and of being a puppet of counterrevolutionaries for attempting to resign his post in protest over the increasing authoritarianism and influence of Communists within the new government. Audience members in the studio include (frames 9-12), Raúl Castro and Che Guevara, apparently present to lend moral force to the speech. Bottom rows of images were taken early that day, before the submission of Matos' resignation, when United States Ambassador Philip W. Bonsal (frames 16, 17, 13, 14, 15) and President Osvaldo Dorticós addressed participants in the annual convention of the American Society of Travel Agents, being held in Havana. Premier Fidel Castro also spoke at the inaugural session that morning. See also Prints 26, 27, 28, 34, 45, 51, 65, 66 and 74.
      - Book VI Print 74: Fidel Castro addressing the American Society of Travel Agents convention in Havana; Fidel Castro giving televised speech denouncing Huber Matos, 1959 October (Box 4, Folder 443)
        Top two rows show Fidel Castro as he waits to be introduced and then addresses delegates as the opening speaker for inaugural morning session of the annual convention of the American Society of Travel Agents (ASTA), held in Havana beginning October 19, 1959. The bottom row of frames shows delegates and speakers, including United States Ambassador Philip W. Bonsal (frame 5 and 6) at the end of the inaugural session. Row three, frames 18-22, depict Fidel Castro giving a televised address to the nation on October 19, 1959, in which he denounced Commander Huber Matos of treason and of being a puppet of counterrevolutionaries for attempting to resign his post in protest over the increasing authoritarianism and influence of Communists within the new government. See also Prints 26, 27, 28, 34, 41, 45, 51, 65 and 74.
    - Contact Book VII
      - Book VII Print 1: Carnival and honeymooning couple, 1960 February (Box 5, Folder 444)
        Street scenes of Carnival in the heart of Centro Habana on El Prado. These images formed part of a story that St. George was doing for Time magazine. The story focused on the honeymoon visit of a couple from New York named Marvin and Phyllis Minoff. The story focused on how recent Cuban government policies and worsening relations with the United States had resulted in the collapse of tourism, which until that point, was largely based on United States travelers. All photographs in this series were taken in mid- to late-February 1960. See also Prints 1, 4, 7, 8, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 25, 26, 27, 29, 30, 37, 39, 41, 42 and 94.
      - Book VII Print 2: School at Camp Columbia, 1960 February-March (Box 5, Folder 445)
        Contains two full sheets of prints. Images of children during morning assembly at the newly constructed school at Camp Columbia, the famous military base originally founded by the U.S. military during the first U.S. occupation of Cuba (1898-1902). Camp Columbia had been the site of the Sergeants' Revolt, led by Fulgencio Batista, against army superiors. This action, taken in favor of the revolutionary movement against the dictator Machado, made Batista an instant national hero until his rupture with Cuba's short-lived revolutionary government in 1933. Thereafter and until 1959, Camp Columbia had been the principal military operations and intelligence depot for the dictator Fulgencio Batista's national army. For this reason, Fidel Castro chose the base as the site from which to make his first speech of triumph to the nation upon his troops' arrival in Havana on the night of January 8, 1959. Camp Columbia was renamed Ciudad Libertad after the founding of the school and it became the first of many army barracks and bases that the government re-crafted as schools in the next several years. Ironically, as the images show, the system of education and cultural values instilled by school programs (such as daily assembly) was highly militarized. See also Prints 6, 9, 32, 33, 34, and 36.
      - Book VII Print 3: Ministry building of the revolutionary government, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 446)
        Contains three sheets. Government building forming part of the new complex of buildings that comprise the ministries of the revolutionary government as of 1960, located in the old La Plaza Cívica, later called La Plaza de la Revolución.
      - Book VII Print 4: Tourists in Cuba, 1960 January-March (Box 5, Folder 447)
        The top four rows of frames show foreign tourists arriving at Havana's international airport where they are greeted by a singing threesome and an official greeter who is giving away woven hats made from yarey, considered a traditional item of clothing worn by Cuban peasants, or guajiros. The greeters formed part of a revolutionary government program to encourage foreign tourism to the island and market symbols of Cuba's newfound sense of national pride as part of the package. Bottom two rows of images show the Minoffs, a honeymooning couple whom St. George accompanied to Cuba for a Time magazine story on the decline of foreign tourism to Cuba during the early period of the Revolution's radicalization (January to March 1960). For images of the Minoffs, see also Prints 1, 7, 8, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 25, 26, 27, 29, 30, 37, 39, 41, 42 and 94. For images of tourists arriving at the airport, see also Prints 26 and 31.
      - Book VII Print 5: First literary conference organized by revolutionary government, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 448)
        The opening session of the first literary conference organized by the revolutionary government. Present are Vilma Espín, Raúl Castro's wife and president of the soon-to-be founded Federación de Mujeres Cubanas. Seated in the audience is Nicolás Guillén, Cuba's future poet laureate and a longtime member of the Communist Party (known as the Partido Socialista Popular from the 1930s through the early 1960s). Speakers include Miguel Angel Asturias, the Guatemalan writer who would win the Nobel Prize in Literature in 1967, as well as Pablo Neruda, the great Chilean poet, also a winner of the Nobel Prize in Literature for 1971. The conference was organized, in part, by Carlos Franqui and other contributing editors of Lunes, a literary and cultural supplement to the official state newspaper, Revolución. Lunes was later eliminated in 1961 for taking positions on the role and nature of cultural freedoms contrary to those espoused by government leaders, especially Fidel Castro. See also Prints 15, 23, 24, 28, 43-52 and 55.
      - Book VII Print 6: School at Camp Columbia; El Morro Fortress repairs, 1960 February-March (Box 5, Folder 449)
        Contains three full sheets and two partial pages. Top and bottom rows of images on one page show boys at the newly inaugurated "Ciudad Escolar Libertad," a school for children of impoverished backgrounds that was founded on the grounds of the previous central military base of the island, Camp Columbia. Remaining images show repairs to the eighteenth-century El Morro Fortress at the mouth of Havana harbor. See also Prints 2, 9, 32, 33, 34, and 36.
      - Book VII Print 7: Honeymooning couple, 1960 February (Box 5, Folder 450)
        Contains three sheets of images. Honeymooning couple, Phyllis and Marvin Minoff, as they watch Cuba's Carnival parade from seats along El Prado, the main street of downtown Havana separating the old colonial city from the early republican-era neighborhoods. Included in the images is the shockingly empty Sloppy Joe's Bar, which would have been full at any other time given that Carnival coincided with the traditional height of the tourist season and the end of the sugar harvest in Cuba, when many Cubans would generally have more spending cash. See also Prints 1, 4, 7, 8, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 25, 26, 27, 29, 30, 31, 37, 41, 42 and 94.
      - Book VII Print 8: Honeymooning couple at race track, 1960 February (Box 5, Folder 451)
        Contains two sheets. The Minoffs visit the race track in Havana at the Casino Deportivo, a sporting complex, where they converse with officials from the newly created Sports Ministry. See also Prints 1, 4, 7, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 25, 27, 29, 30, 31, 37, 41, 42 and 94.
      - Book VII Print 9: School at Camp Columbia, 1960 February-March (Box 5, Folder 452)
        Contains three sheets. Images of children on the playground at the newly constructed school, "Ciudad Libertad," on the former military base of Camp Columbia, Havana. Camp Columbia had been the site of the Sergeants' Revolt, led by Fulgencio Batista, against army superiors. This action, taken in favor of the revolutionary movement against the dictator Machado, made Batista an instant national hero until his rupture with Cuba's short-lived revolutionary government in 1933. Thereafter and until 1959, Camp Columbia had been the principal military operations and intelligence depot for the dictator Fulgencio Batista's national army. Consequently, the transformation of Camp Columbia into a place for the educational uplift of peasants acquired particular symbolic value after the Revolution. Ironically, as the images show, the system of education and cultural values instilled by school programs (such as daily assembly) were highly militarized. See also Prints 2, 6, 32, 33, 34, and 36.
      - Book VII Print 10: Honeymooning couple at casino; tourists at Hotel Nacional, 1960 February (Box 5, Folder 453)
        Based on St. George's own submission notes enclosed in this file, these images show the Minoffs at the casino at the Hotel Caprí, entirely deserted of all tourists, which is located on the famous street called La Rampa that connects the central area surrounding the University of Havana to the Malecón, or sea wall. The only people sitting in the casino besides the Minoffs and the dealer are two off-duty showgirls from the nightclub at El Caprí and what he calls a "b-girl," or free-lance and high-class prostitute. Other images in the prints show a group of foreigners lounging alongside the pool at the Hotel Nacional. See also Prints 1, 4, 7, 8, 11, 12, 13, 14, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 25, 26, 27, 29, 30, 31, 37, 41, 42 and 94.
      - Book VII Print 11: Honeymooning couple at casino, 1960 February (Box 5, Folder 454)
        Continuation (on two sheets) of casino shots shown in Print 10. Also includes more images of the Minoffs enjoying the spectacle of Carnival on El Prado (see also Prints 1 and 7) while uniformed members of the national revolutionary police look on. See also Prints 1, 4, 7, 8, 10, 12, 13, 14, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 25, 26, 27, 29, 30, 31, 37, 41, 42 and 94.
      - Book VII Print 12: Honeymooning couple at casino and swimming, 1960 February (Box 5, Folder 455)
        Continuation of casino shots shown in Prints 10 and 11. Also included is Mrs. Phyllis Minoff in the swimming pool at the Hotel Caprí, again entirely deserted of all tourists. See also Prints 1, 4, 7, 8, 10, 11, 13, 14, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 25, 26, 27, 29, 30, 31, 37, 41, 42 and 94.
      - Book VII Print 13: Jean Paul Sartre and Simone de Beauvoir; honeymooning couple on El Prado, 1960 March (Box 5, Folder 456)
        Contains one full sheet and two torn strips. Images of Jean Paul Sartre, his wife and equally prominent intellectual, Simone de Beauvoir, and several unidentified men talking and lounging poolside at the Hotel Nacional. Sitting on the floor at de Beauvoir's feet is Robert Taber, CBS News correspondent and previous collaborator with St. George for stories on Raúl Castro's guerrilla column in the Sierra Maestra in July 1958. Also included at the bottom of the full sheet and on a partial strip are images of the Minoffs shopping for souvenirs on El Prado, downtown Havana, at night. For more on the Minoffs, see Prints 1, 4, 7, 8, 10, 11, 12, 14, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 25, 26, 27, 29, 30, 31, 37, 41 and 42.; for more on the Sartre and de Beauvoir visit, see Prints 10, 14, 16, 18, 19 and Book VIII.
      - Book VII Print 14: Honeymooning couple at Hotel Capri; Jean Paul Sartre and Simone de Beauvoir, 1960 March (Box 5, Folder 457)
        Contains two sheets. Top frames show Phyllis and Marvin Minoff admiring the view of La Rampa, a commercial and entertainment strip in el Vedado, a neighborhood of Havana, from a viewing window at the Hotel Caprí. Bottom images show Jean Paul Sartre, his wife and equally prominent intellectual, Simone de Beauvoir, and several unidentified men talking and lounging poolside at the Hotel Nacional. Sitting on the floor at de Beauvoir's feet is Robert Taber, CBS News correspondent and previous collaborator with St. George for stories on Raúl Castro's guerrilla column in the Sierra Maestra in July 1958. These hotels are within walking distance of one another in el Vedado, Havana. For more on the Minoffs, see Prints 1, 4, 7, 8, 10, 11, 12, 13, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 25, 26, 27, 29, 30, 31, 37, 41 and 42; for more on the Sartre and de Beauvoir visit, see Prints 10, 13 16, 18, 19 and Book VIII.
      - Book VII Print 15: First literary conference organized by revolutionary government, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 458)
        Scenes from the first conference on Latin American literature organized by sectors of Cuba's revolutionary government. Present are Vilma Espín, Raúl Castro's wife and president of the soon-to-be founded Federación de Mujeres Cubanas. Speakers include Miguel Angel Asturias, the Guatemalan writer who would win the Nobel Prize in Literature in 1967, as well as Pablo Neruda, the great Chilean poet, also a winner of the Nobel Prize in Literature for 1971. The conference was organized, in part, by Carlos Franqui and other contributing editors of Lunes, a literary and cultural supplement to the official state newspaper, Revolución. Lunes was later eliminated in 1961 for taking positions on the role and nature of cultural freedoms contrary to those espoused by government leaders, especially Fidel Castro. See also Prints 5, 23, 24, 28, 43-52 and 55.
      - Book VII Print 16: Jean Paul Sartre and Simone de Beauvoir, 1960 March (Box 5, Folder 459)
        Middle frames of this sheet show Jean Paul Sartre, his wife and equally prominent intellectual, Simone de Beauvoir, and several unidentified men talking and lounging poolside at the Hotel Nacional. Sitting on the floor at de Beauvoir's feet and standing and leaning against the door in the top row of frames and bottom is Robert Taber, CBS News correspondent and previous collaborator with St. George for stories on Raúl Castro's guerrilla column in the Sierra Maestra in July 1958. See also Prints 10, 13, 14, 16, 18, 19 and Book VIII.
      - Book VII Print 17: Honeymooning couple at beach and casino, 1960 February-March (Box 5, Folder 460)
        Honeymooning couple, Phyllis and Marvin Minoff, whom St. George accompanied to Cuba for a story on the decline in foreign tourism. Here they are seen cavorting at Varadero beach. Very bottom images show the Minoffs at the Hotel Caprí casino. See also Prints 1, 4, 7, 8, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 25, 26, 27, 29, 30, 31, 37, 41 and 42.
      - Book VII Print 18: Tourists and Jean Paul Sartre and Simone de Beauvoir at Hotel Nacional, 1960 March (Box 5, Folder 461)
        Unidentified foreign female, probably a tourist, sitting in one of the chairs in the center courtyard of the Hotel Nacional, el Vedado, Havana. Top frames show her in the company of an unknown shirtless man of advanced years, possibly her father. The second row of frames shows Simone de Beauvoir, Jean Paul Sartre, and another unidentified foreign couple having lunch poolside at the Hotel Nacional. See also Prints 10, 13 16, 18, 19 and Book VIII.
      - Book VII Print 19: Socialist Youth street demonstration; tourists at Hotel Nacional, 1960 March (Box 5, Folder 462)
        Contains one sheet and one strip. Frames at the very top of the sheet show a street demonstration staged by the Socialist Youth (Juventud Socialista) on San Rafael Boulevard in Havana. Their signs show their support for the government's recent call that all workers contribute one day's pay to the purchase of arms and military weapons for the national defense of Cuba against counterrevolutionary forces. The second and third row of frames show one of the privately-owned shops that line one of the corridors near the main lobby at the Hotel Nacional, el Vedado, Havana. Bottom three rows of frames show an unidentified foreign female tourist sitting in one of the chairs in the center courtyard of the Hotel Nacional. For more images of the Minoffs, see Prints 1, 4, 7, 8, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 17, 18, 20, 21, 22, 25, 26, 27, 29, 30, 31, 37, 41, 42 and 94. For more images of the unidentified tourist, see Print 18.
      - Book VII Print 20: Honeymooning couple on the Malecón, 1960 February-March (Box 5, Folder 463)
        Contains three sheets. The Minoffs walking on the Malecón, or sea wall, after doing some souvenir shopping in Havana. Phyllis Minoff carries a small, handcrafted souvenir doll in one hand. See also Prints 1, 4, 7, 8, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 17, 18, 21, 22, 25, 26, 27, 29, 30, 31, 37, 41 and 42.
      - Book VII Print 21: Honeymooning couple at beach resort, 1960 February-March (Box 5, Folder 464)
        Contains two sheets. The Minoffs at a beach resort in Varadero. A series of photographs shows them examining what appears to be a souvenir item of a sculpted garza or type of crane common to Cuba's mangroves. The man who is showing them the souvenirs may be trying to sell them; these sculptures were often carved from white coral. Top frames of second sheet show the Minoffs on the beach with the hotel visible in the distance. See also Prints 1, 4, 7, 8, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 17, 18, 20, 22, 26, 27, 29, 30, 31, 37, 41, 42 and 94.
      - Book VII Print 22: Honeymooning couple at beach resort; militia boys on beach patrol, 1960 February-March (Box 5, Folder 465)
        Contains two sheets. Phyllis and Marvin Minoff at the beach resort pictured in Print 21. Frames 15 and 16 of the second sheet are particularly significant because they show two very young teenage boys who are carrying automatic weapons, ostensibly because they are militiamen assigned to protect the shore from any possible sabotage or unauthorized landings by counterrevolutionaries. See also Prints 1, 4, 7, 8, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 17, 18, 20, 21, 25, 26, 27, 29, 30, 31, 37, 41, 42 and 94.
      - Book VII Print 23: First literary conference organized by revolutionary government, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 466)
        Scenes from sessions of the first conference on Latin American literature organized by sectors of the revolutionary government. Present are Vilma Espín, Raúl Castro's wife and president of the soon-to-be founded Federación de Mujeres Cubanas, and Nicolás Guillén, Cuba's future poet laureate and a longtime member of the Communist Party (known as the Partido Socialista Popular from the 1930s through the early 1960s). Speakers include Miguel Angel Asturias, the Guatemalan writer who would win the Nobel Prize in Literature in 1967, as well as Pablo Neruda, the great Chilean poet, also a winner of the Nobel Prize in Literature for 1971. The conference was organized, in part, by Carlos Franqui and other contributing editors of Lunes, a literary and cultural supplement to the official state newspaper, Revolución. Lunes was later eliminated in 1961 for taking positions on the role and nature of cultural freedoms contrary to those espoused by government leaders, especially Fidel Castro. This sheet features closeup shots of various impassioned writers as they address the audience. The top three rows show an unidentified older woman speaking with another woman, possibly a translator at her side. See also Prints 15, 24, 28, 43-52 and 55.
      - Book VII Print 24: First literary conference organized by revolutionary government, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 467)
        Scenes from sessions of the first conference on Latin American literature organized by sectors of the revolutionary government. Present are Vilma Espín, Raúl Castro's wife and president of the soon-to-be founded Federación de Mujeres Cubanas and Nicolás Guillén, Cuba's future poet laureate and a longtime member of the Communist Party (known as the Partido Socialista Popular from the 1930s through the early 1960s). Speakers include Miguel Angel Asturias, the Guatemalan writer who would win the Nobel Prize in Literature in 1967, as well as Pablo Neruda, the great Chilean poet, also a winner of the Nobel Prize in Literature for 1971. The conference was organized, in part, by Carlos Franqui and other contributing editors of Lunes, a literary and cultural supplement to the official state newspaper, Revolución. Lunes was later eliminated in 1961 for taking positions on the role and nature of cultural freedoms contrary to those espoused by government leaders, especially Fidel Castro. Top frames of this sheet feature closeup shots of an unidentified Asian man speaking through an interpreter; Vilma Espín dozes off in the audience in frames 11-13. See also Prints 5, 15, 23, 28, 43-52 and 55.
      - Book VII Print 25: Honeymooning couple on fishing trip, 1960 February-March (Box 5, Folder 468)
        Contains two sheets and two strips. Honeymooners featured in St. George's Time magazine story highlighting the decline of foreign tourism in Cuba. Phyllis and Marvin Minoff embark on a deep-sea fishing trip and take a small plane there. The plane is empty of all passengers except for the Minoffs and photographer. It is likely that the fishing trip took place near the Ciénaga de Zapata, a mangrove-lined swamp famous for its fishing and crocodiles in south-central Cuba. Frames 3-6 of the second sheet show Marvin Minoff holding a rifle off the edge of a boat and shooting at something, most likely a crocodile. See also Prints 1, 4, 7, 8, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 17, 18, 20, 21, 26, 27, 29, 30, 31, 37, 41, 42 and 94.
      - Book VII Print 26: Honeymooning couple at beach; tourists arriving in Havana, 1960 February-March (Box 5, Folder 469)
        Top four frames show Phyllis and Marvin Minoff lounging on a seaside dock at Varadero beach. Bottom two rows feature images of foreign tourists arriving at Havana international airport where they are greeted by a trio of musicians and a woman offering a yarey hat. For more images of the Minoffs, see also Prints 1, 4, 7, 8, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 17, 18, 20, 21, 25, 27, 29, 30, 37, 41 and 42; for more images of tourists arriving at the Havana airport, see Prints also 4 and 31.
      - Book VII Print 27: Honeymooning couple at Carnival, 1960 February-March (Box 5, Folder 470)
        This print shows Phyllis and Marvin Minoff enjoying Carnival in Havana and a meal at an opulent restaurant. The absence of tourists, as well as all other diners, is striking, as the entire wait staff of the restaurant dotes on the one occupied table. See also Prints 1, 4, 7, 8, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 17, 18, 20, 21, 25, 26, 29, 30, 37, 41, 42 and 94.
      - Book VII Print 28: First literary conference organized by the revolutionary government, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 471)